my name is Olushola Jagede
I'm a Chartered Accountant
professionally a Chartered Accountant
in both Nigeria and in Sierra Leone
a fellow of the Institute of Chartered Accountants
in Sierra Leone
in April 2026
I presented to Icasa members in Freetown
on the question of what artificial intelligence means
for the South African professionals
not in theory
in practice for the people in that room
I want to share the call of that argument with you now
because I think it is most important thing
any professional in Sierra Leone
can undertake about this technology
honestly
these are part of my observation
I made to my colleagues at I Castle
and I will make it here without softening it
my professional colleagues in Sierra Leone
in lot of them
are currently using AI as a search engine
with a friendlier interface and I claw for them
they type a question they read the answer
they use it and they do not
at times
they have not yet understood what it actually is
or what it can actually do when it is used properly
and the professionals who are not using it at all
the ones who have decided
it does not apply to their work
or that it is passing novelty
or that they will engage with it
when it becomes more readable
these professionals are already behind
not a little by a gap that is widening every month
I'm not saying this to alarm you no
I'm saying it because
the same professionals who are currently behind
are also the ones who have the most to gain
I repeat it again
I'm not raising this issue to alarm you
I'm saying it because
the same professionals who are currently behind
are also the ones who have the most to gain
because of what you already know
to understand what AI actually is
I want to introduce a distinction that I think
clarifies everything
cold data and warm data
yes cold
and you might be thinking
can data be cold or can it be warm
sure some data can be very cold and some can be warm
so what is cold data
cold data is what AI brings
it is vast it is fast
it is accurate at scale it has read more text
than any human being will read in hundred lifetime
that's AI
what any human being will read a hundred lifetimes
AI has read it
it can recognize patterns across millions of documents
it can produce professional language in seconds
it never gets tired
it is never in a bad mood
it is never distracted
by what happened before the meeting
but cold data
does not know who is reading the documents
no
vast
fast
with unlimited knowledge patterns
yet cold data does not know what is reading
or who is reading document
it does not know the history between your organization
and the ministry you are writing to
it does not know that this particular director respond
badly to passive voice and well
to direct this
it does not know that the regulation is just
is just cited was amended six months ago
it does not know
what is politically sensitive this month
in your sector
it does not know what your client needs to feel
when they finish reading your letter
there are several things AI does not know yet
very fast
have unlimited data unlimited information
but that's everything does not know so what is one data
and warm data is what you bring
that's what you bring
cold data is what AI brings
but warm data is what you bring
now what is warm data
warm data is your specific
applied knowledge of your field
your years of navigating real situations
your understanding of the people you work with
or you work for
your understanding of the institutions they represent
your understanding of the value of your institution
your understanding of the people
and the cultural fluency
your professional judgment about what is appropriate
in this moment for this particular recipient or client
cold data and warm data are not competing
no they are not competing
they are complementary AI
as is most powerful
is cold data multiplied by warm data
you want to have the best of AI
it is a combination of cold data
multiplied by warm data the warmer the data you bring
the more specific the more experience
the more professional deep
the better the Output
Friends AI does not replace you
it multiplies you
yes I'm saying it again
AI does not replace you it multiplies you
at I Castle during the meeting that I facilitated
I described five stages of professional evolution
in the age of AI
let me quickly walk you through them quickly
because I want you to know where you are standing
right now maybe stage one
stage two stage three
stage four stage five
in the stage one that's what I call the Record keeper
at this level
the professional processes and stores information
produces documentation as a function of role
has not yet recognized
the strategic value of the information they handle
is just about keeping records
oh stage two is a bit better
it's an improvement on stage one
the analyzer
they interpret and crystallize data
begins to see patterns
can even explain what the information means
not just what it says
there's an improvement on C2
which is strategist
they use professional knowledge
to anticipate consequences
advice rather than report
it's not just about report
they use to advice the information they produce
shape decision
the strategies but be after strategies
we have the integrator
the integrator connects knowledge across the means
sees relationship between fields
produce synthesis that neither AI
no junior professional will produce alone
AI alone cannot produce it
a junior professional cannot cannot
cannot produce it because this integrator
they connect knowledge across the means
since relationship between feels and produce synthesis
like I said that neither AI
nor a general professional
could produce the Baba of all of them
that's the five that the architect of valor
yeah why I say architect of values
yes architect of values
the design system
design frameworks and approaches
that create durable institutional capacity
this is what they do that's what they do
they design systems they design frameworks
the design approaches
that create durable institutional capacity
their professional knowledge produces value
that outlast their individual presence
even when they are not there
what they produce actually outlast them
here is what AI changes about this ladder
like I said I mentioned five stages
I say stage 1 the Record Keeper
stage 2 the Analyser
stage 3 the strategist
stage 4 the Integrator
Stage stage 5
the architect of values
this is where you should be working towards
where you design system you design framework
you design approaches
that create durable institutional capacity
your professional knowledge produces value
that outlasts your individual presence
and here is what AI changes about this ladder
the professionals at stage 1 and two
that the record keeper and the analyzer
are most at risk of displacement
not because AI will take their jobs no
but because the value of record keeping
and basic analysis drops sharply
when AI can do it faster and cheaper
AI is not the one displacing you no
but AI is not taking your job also no
but the value of your record keeping and basic analysis
AI can do it faster
AI can do it cheaper
the professionals at Stage 3 and Stage 4 and stage 5
become dramatically more valuable if they engage AI
because they are using AI
to produce more of what only they can produce
more of what only they can produce
there's judgement there's synthesis
there's strategy and there's institutional wisdom
AI does not push you down the ladder no
it accelerates your climb up
but only if you use it and only if you use it properly
I say it again AI does not push you down this ladder no
it accelerates your climb up
but only if you use it and only if you use it properly
I want to say something that I do not hear said enough
in conversation about AI in Africa
a number of people talk about AI
but in Africa there's something I've not had enough
that it seldom comes up and what is it
AI was primarily trained on western English speaking
high income context it does not know a great deal
about our professional communication works
in Sierra Leone
it knows about London knows about New York
New knows about Sydney
it knows considerably less or does not know much how
former correspondence war
between Freetown Angel and the Ministry of education
or between Shattered Accountant
and the National Revenue Authority
in Sri Lanka AI doesn't know it
AI can tell you top notch information about London
about New York about Sydney
but several things you may not
know about the internal policies in Sierra Leone
it doesn't
the professional in Sierra Leone
who understand the local regulatory landscape
the cultural conventions of formal correspondence
the relationship dynamics between specific institution
the language that lands well with a particular ministry
and the language that does not
that professional has one data that no AI model has
I repeat it again
irrespective of the AI model you are using
because you are a professional based in Freetown
you understand the local regulatory landscape
the cultural conventions of formal correspondences
your relations between people and institution
the language of the land
you are possess a warm data that no AI model has
when that professional
lose their local knowledge into AI
maybe you are the professional
maybe when you lose that's your local knowledge into AI
the output is dramatically better
than anything a generic user
in another part of the world
would produce
with the same tool and the same free asset
a professional who is based either in New York
in Australia in any part of the world
with the same tool of AI
who does not have the local knowledge of Sierra Leone
cannot match you when you combine your knowledge
of the local environment with the tool
your local knowledge is not a limitation
in the age of AI
it is your most powerful professional asset
your local knowledge is not a limitation no
I want to speak directly to the professional
who is watching this and thinking
this is interesting
but I will engage with it when I have more time
there's no more time brother
sister there's no more time
colleagues there's no more time
the window to move from observer to practitioner
is not staying open indefinitely
the professionals who build this capacity now
will be significantly ahead
of those who build it in two years
not marginally ahead significantly
the professionals who chose
who deliberate make a choice
to build their capacity in the use of AI now
will be significantly ahead
of those who build it in two years time
not marginally ahead significantly ahead
and the cost of engaging is low
the tools are free
the knowledge required is what you already have
that's your local knowledge
the only thing that needs to change
is the decision to take the first professional step
this course is that step I'm glad you are taking it
finally brothers
friends cold data is what the machine brings
warm data is what you bring
the combination of cold data and warm data
produce something neither could produce alone
and it makes you better than any professional
out of your local environment
who have access to the same tool of AI
the cloud is moving it is now for you to move in